Good morning.
Today I decided not to use PowerPoint.
I'm using index cards.
This is traditional lecture style.
I wanted to talk today about, this is our third lecture for
financial markets, and I wanted to talk today about invention
in finance.
And this is about, I think of finance, I don't know whether
this will encourage you to be interested or not, but I think
of it as a form of engineering.
Finance is all about inventions, devices that solve
problems and that help people do things and get on with their
purposes in life.
And the inventions have many small details, just like any
invention.
Like this.
It's like an airplane.
If you look at an airplane, how many parts are in there?
How many different people worked on the different parts?
And it's so complicated that you might have disbelief that
this whole thing is going to work, but somehow it does work.
Another part that I want to emphasize in today's lecture
is that engineering requires a human element.
And engineers know that their devices will be run by people.
And people are imperfect.
And so, they have a course in engineering schools called
Human Factors Engineering.
And that's about designing machines so that human beings
won't mess up when they try to use them.
And so, that gets us into psychology.
So, I think, to me, when we talk about behavioral findings,
which is going to be a theme of this course, human psychology
and finance, it's fundamental to the inventive side of
finance.
So, that's what I want to talk about.
I'm going to give you some examples of invention and talk
about how they solve the risk problem, the fundamental
problem of maintaining incentives in the face of risks.
But before I start this lecture, I wanted to just briefly review
the last lecture.
Which was a very important lecture for this course.
Because it talked about the underlying probability theory
and applications of probability theory to finance.
So, let me just mention some of the concepts that I talked
about last time.
The first one was return.
We talked about the return on an investment, which has two
components.
The capital gain, which is the increase in the price of the
investment.
And the other is the dividend, which is something that comes
separately as in the form of a check, maybe, or an electronic
entry.
But we then moved quickly to probability theory.
We talked about random variables.
A random variable is a quantity that's created by some kind of
experiment or event that is uncertain in advance and becomes
known later.
And then we talked about measures.
We talked about the probability distribution.
We talked about probability distribution.
We talked about probability distributions.
We talked about central tendency.
And we talked about the average or mean and the geometric
average.
And we talked about measures of risk.
Notably, variance.
But then there's also measures of co-movement between two
factors.
So, we talked about variance and correlation.
And we talked about regression.
And then finally, we talked about distributions of random
variables and the normal distribution, which is famous.
It's the famous bell-shaped curve, which is thought by many
people to represent a typical distribution.
And it's one of the failures of the assumption.
The idea of independent random variables that are normally
distributed is a powerful idea.
We have some idea that there's a bell-shaped curve, and we know
something about what relates to what and what doesn't relate to
what.
And these ideas are partly intuitive, and they're partly
wrong.
And so, the concluding element of the last lecture was that the
financial crisis that has enveloped the world in the
world, starting around 2007, seems to be related to people's
failure to understand the limits of the independence
assumption they were making.
And also, to the limits of the normal distribution, namely,
failure to consider outliers.
So, let's just think about independence briefly for a
moment.
It's inherent in the intuitive view we have of the world.
If you toss a coin, every time you toss it, you think, each
toss has to be independent of the previous toss.
They're not going to come up the same, because there's
nothing relating the two tosses.
So, you have a strong intuitive sense that some events are
independent.
You might also think that returns on the stock market from
day to day are independent.
Why is that?
Well, because they relate to news.
Right?
You can't use the stock market on any day.
It's news.
And by definition, news has to be new.
So, it can't just be yesterday's news.
So, it has to be something fresh.
And I showed you a plot of the stock market and of Apple stock.
And in this plot, it came out that the stocks look roughly
independent, the returns from day to day.
But they're not necessarily independent, and they can
surprise you.
And that's when crises occurs.
We also talked about idiosyncratic risk and market
risk.
Remember, we regressed Apple stock's returns on the stock
market's returns.
And then we got a fitted value, which was beta times the market
return.
And that's the market component of Apple risk.
And then we saw that the extra component, idiosyncratic, is
uncorrelated with the market risk.
But in this case, it's uncorrelated by construction.
So, it has to be uncorrelated.
Oh, by the way, I don't know if you caught the news.
It's just coincidence that I mentioned Apple stock in my
last lecture.
You must have heard the news.
It was headline news in the Wall Street Journal.
We had a three-day weekend because of the Martin Luther
King holiday in the U.S.
And over the weekend, Apple announced that Steve Jobs is
taking a long break.
And he was on leave of absence from Apple because of his
health.
And so, we talked about that.
Steve Jobs is viewed by a lot of people as the genius behind
Apple.
And the last time he left for a long time, Apple didn't do
well.
And so, you wonder what would happen to the stock.
Well, since they announced it on a day just before the market
was closed.
It opened in Europe.
And there was a 7% drop in Germany of Apple shares.
It opened down 5% on Tuesday in the U.S.
But then it recovered.
And it wasn't really down that much.
Probably because there was good earnings news at the same time.
That's just completing our little story about Apple.
So, I want to say something.
I don't know if I gave enough emphasis to the central limit
theorem yesterday, last lecture.
This is a fundamental theorem from probability theory, which
says that if you have independent identity, you can
distribute identically distributed random variables.
That is, every random variable is independent of the other,
and they all have the same distribution.
And if it has a finite variance, then the distribution of an
average distribution of a random variable, which is a finite
average of these variables, converges to the normal distribution
as the number of elements in the average is increased.
In other words, averages are approximately normally distributed.
The bell-shaped curve works as well as it does, because so many
things we observe in nature are averages.
So many things that we observe are the sum of many effects.
This is what history is all about.
Anytime big events occur, it's probably because a number of
things chance to happen at the same time.
And that's why probability theorists think that we know,
we kind of know the probability distribution of, and that's this
bell-shaped curve, which I had on a slide last period.
The critical thing about the bell-shaped curve is that the
tails drop off really fast after you get a certain distance out.
And either way, they essentially hit zero.
They never hit zero.
The probability is never zero that anything can happen with a
normally distributed variable.
But the normal distribution does not have fat tails.
After two or three or four standard deviations, basically
the probability is zero that that kind of thing will happen,
that it returns.
And we can't even predict the return if we're applying it to
returns, that that would occur.
So, the problem with the central limit theorem is that
it's only as good as its assumptions.
And it assumes that the underlying variables have a
finite variance.
That they themselves are not so fat-tailed that the variance of
them is infinite.
And in fact, that assumption might be wrong.
Because we see, especially in finance, we see big outliers
coming from time to time.
And so, I have to present a theory and say, I like the
theory, the central limit theorem is an important theory,
but it's also wrong.
That's the problem with financial theory.
It's not quite as good as the theory that physicists or
chemists use.
It has its limitations.
Nonetheless, that's what we have to talk about.
And we have to make do with that as much as we can.
I wanted to just correct, also, I'm almost done with my review
of the last lecture.
I wanted to just correct what I said.
I said that fat-tailed distributions were discovered
by Benoit Mandelbrot.
But that's, I have to give credit properly, it's actually
his teacher, so I've got this now.
There was Pierre, I'm sorry, Paul Pierre Lévy, was a
mathematician who lived from 1886 to 1971, who really first
developed the theory of fat-tailed distribution.
And he was at the École Polytechnique de l'Histoire,
Polytechnique in France.
And his student was Benoit Mandelbrot, who was one of the
great mathematicians.
Well, they were both among the great mathematicians of the
20th century.
So, I think we, our knowledge of fat-tailed distribution
comes down to us through word of mouth.
From Lévy, who was Mandelbrot's teacher, to
Mandelbrot, to me, and then to you, I think.
So, we don't require any printed word to know this.
That's the way the history of thought goes.
So, there's an old joke about the normal distribution.
It said that, the joke goes as follows.
The mathematicians think that the normal distribution is
ubiquitous in nature because of the fact that the distribution
is ubiquitous.
And the fact is, the distribution is ubiquitous in
nature because applied workers have discovered that everything
is normally distributed.
But applied workers think that the normal distribution is
ubiquitous in nature because mathematicians have proved that
it's ubiquitous in nature.
In fact, it's sort of ubiquitous, but it sort of
surprises you.
And that's one of the fundamental lessons in finance.
The fundamental lesson in finance is that you might go
into a business and you're observing some random return or
some random variable in finance.
And you kind of think you know how it behaves, and you've
learned some confidence.
There will come a day when it defies all of your expectations.
And that's what fat tails are about.
So, OK, I want to move on now to today's lecture, which is
about invention.
And particularly, financial invention.
And a lot of, how should I start here?
Let me start by recalling how much finance has changed since
19-
1970.
OK, that's 40 years ago.
In 1970, there were no options exchanges.
Well, there were options, but they were not traded on any
exchange.
There were no financial futures.
There were no swaps.
I haven't defined what these things are for you.
What else did they not have?
They didn't have electronic trading.
They would do trading by word of mouth.
They would meet together on the floor of an exchange and shout
at each other and talk.
I guess they had telephones, but it was all words and people.
And writing on paper.
So, that's the proliferation of financial instruments in 40 years
is stunning.
And so, I wanted to use that as a springboard to think about,
what is the next 40 years going to be like?
And if any of you go into finance, this will be your career.
I think that it's reasonable to suppose that the transformation in the
next 40 years is going to be just as dramatic as the last 40
years, or more so.
Because technical progress doesn't slow down.
I don't see any reason to think that it's slowing down.
So, I like to think about the future, but it's hard to talk
about the future, because we're not there yet.
I've written a couple of books.
One of them is really about the future of finance.
And I think it's really important to think about the future of
finance.
One of them is called Macro Markets, which I wrote in 1993,
about the big market.
Macro means big markets that we'll be seeing in the future.
And the other one was called New Financial Order, which I wrote
in 2003.
And we have the introductory chapter there on the reading
list for this lecture.
But the basic, what I see is happening with all of these,
the big markets, and the big markets, and the big markets
are the ones that are going to be the big markets.
Incidentally, we have a lot of questioning of these inventions
now, because they kind of blew up on us in this financial
crisis.
So, it's a little bit like after an airplane crash, people
are kind of critical of the aeronautical engineers for a
while.
Or when they invented steam engines, some of them blew up.
And it was bad.
You know, when a boiler blows up, it scalds all the people
who were mad at them for a while.
I think that's what we're going through now.
And people are angry about some of these inventions.
But that's just part of progress.
Well, it doesn't mean that we don't want to regulate them.
We regulate boilers and airplanes right now to prevent
crashes, and we need to regulate our financial markets
just as well.
But, yeah.
Thank you.
So, the financial markets that we have, they're based on
mathematical models.
This is a mathematical discipline, but the
mathematical models depend only on certain intuition.
Maybe a core part of the intuition that underlies the
financial inventions is the idea of independence.
And that if risks are, I'm going to try and talk in
really basic terms.
If risks are independent of each other, then we can pull
them and they go away.
That's the core idea.
But how to make that happen requires some thought and some
devices.
The intuitive idea that we can exploit independence to improve
our lives goes back to ancient times, actually.
A lot of things that people do are done in recognition of what
is independent and what is not.
I think even in big causes that people get emotional about over
the ages are causes that, I can think of them as examples of the
probability theory in modern finance.
So, you might not agree with me, but this is my view of it.
Think of socialism.
What is socialism?
Well, you know it was invented by the philosopher or
entrepreneur Robert Owen.
The word was invented by him in the early 19th century.
But what is it?
It is that society gets together and pools all of its activities.
And I think, well, why would you want to do that?
Well, one reason you do that is that it improves
human welfare, because it shares risks.
And we're all in it together, and we won't have rich and poor.
I think that's part of Robert Owen's idea.
He was worried about inequality, that some people are much better
off than others, and that's bad.
And so, let's create a socialist society.
So, he had an invention of sorts, but it didn't seem to be a very
– in his form, it was not a very successful invention, because
there was –
it didn't work somehow.
He set up a town called New Harmony in the United States,
which was supposed to be harmonious by the name of the town,
and everything was shared.
And unfortunately, they ended up arguing and fighting
amongst each other, and they were not happy.
He didn't get it figured out right.
He was trying to pool risks, but he didn't do it.
There are other idealistic societies that try to do it,
like the kibbutzim in Israel, but that's one of many,
where people get together and do it.
They get together and form a community, and they pool
everything, and it kind of works for some people.
But only a tiny fraction of the population in Israel lives on a
kibbutz now.
Why not?
I think most people just don't fit in that way.
We share everything.
After a few months living there, you might think, I'm out of here.
I don't want to share everything with everybody.
So, people do things.
And in the old west, the pioneers in America, they had
kind of a social compact that if one farmer's house burned
down, everyone will come by and help and erect a new house for
that person.
So, that's, again, risk management.
And it works.
It sounds almost like a moral thing, but it works only
because they don't all burn down at the same time.
It would be totally worthless if they all did.
And so, there are primitive ideas of insurance that underlie
that, but the ideas aren't worked out well.
And it doesn't, perhaps, work well to do it on such an
informal basis.
So, our society has particular inventions that, we call them
financial or insurance inventions, that make these
things work better.
And so, what we're talking about is motivated by theory.
And the mathematical theory of finance.
But that's not the subject of this course.
I want to, in this course, talk more about the inventions
themselves.
And in particular, we'll be talking about risk management.
Now, this brings up a basic issue about finance.
Is finance good?
Is it helpful to people?
A huge issue.
A huge issue in the history of humankind is inequality.
And that people get upset when it seems like other people
have an unfair advantage over us.
But inequality is something that you'd think finance
works against.
Modern finance is about risk management.
So, you can get rid of the purely random element in
people's lives.
That should make people more equal.
And it should be a good thing.
That is the way I view it.
And the other side of finance is that it also creates
opportunity.
And opportunity is very important also.
We can all be equal in living in poverty, and we don't
particularly like that.
So, that's why financial inventions eventually inspire
and get people excited.
I always remember Deng Xiaoping's famous statement in
the late 1970s, when China was adopting modern financial
methods, and some people were getting rich.
And someone asked Deng, isn't this inconsistent with our
ideology?
And then he said, well, I'm quoting him approximately,
we're all going to get rich, but somebody has to get rich
first.
And that's the way it is.
Financial markets, they do manage risk, but they also
create opportunities, and that can actually increase
inequality.
So, you have to consider both sides of this.
So, maybe the most important concept in finance really is
risk.
And risk is all about limiting inequality, or at least the
random, gratuitous inequality, right?
People are troubled by, you know, the idea that you can
get rich, but you're troubled by inequality if it's arbitrary.
But, you know, most people won't begrudge someone who
works very hard and shows real genius and insight and makes a
lot of money.
Most people say that's all right.
But we have trouble dealing, now, part of the way we deal
with risk is our taxes, tax and welfare system.
So, our tax and welfare, I'm going to come back to that
mostly in our last, second to the last lecture.
But we have a progressive income tax that taxes rich
people more, and we have welfare.
And we also, I should add, it's not counted as welfare, but
free public education, which is a form of, I wouldn't call it
welfare, but it's equalizing expenditure.
These are actually our most important risk management
devices.
That's what makes life tolerable in modern society,
that we do have progressive taxes and welfare.
But we don't rely on those exclusively.
And so, finance is getting into the other dimensions.
And we kind of want to let insurance, private insurance,
rather than social insurance flourish.
Because when the government handles everything, it doesn't
matter what the government does.
It doesn't matter what the government does.
It doesn't seem to work as effectively or creatively as it
can if we let private entrepreneurs handle things.
So, what we're talking about here, to always put it in
perspective, what we're talking about in this course is about
something that is an add-on to an existing welfare and taxes
system, but an add-on that is, we hope, particularly effective.
And it's added on by people in their own self-interest, or
maybe for their own purposes, but something that ultimately
contributes to, I think, a better world.
And that's what I want to.
So, I have several themes in this.
The first is a risk theme, which I've just discussed.
Another theme I want to talk about here is a framing theme.
And that is that psychologists use the term framing to refer
to the context and associations that we have with something.
So, the way people use things depends on what they see them
associated with, because people can't think through to the
fundamental theory all the time.
So, we have to frame things in a way that's convenient to people.
And this is part of financial engineering.
I'll come back to that in a minute.
But then.
But framing has to do with language and names that we give to things.
We have to design inventions so that they are framed in good ways.
We'll explain that in a minute.
And then I have a device theme.
That finance is really about devices, like steam engines.
We call them financial contracts.
And devices are complicated structures that we set up for a certain purpose.
And like airplanes or automobiles.
And we learn through time how to make them better and better.
And they tend to get.
They tend to come on the world with a flourish, a surprise.
There's some new invention.
You know, when the Wright brothers first exhibited the airplane in the Paris Air Show in 1904,
I think, and people were stunned.
They were actually flying.
And it immediately set up around the world, the aircraft industry.
If you look around the world, these devices look very similar.
Automobiles, airplanes, they look almost the same in every country.
But that's because they have an internal logic to them that makes them work well.
And the logic may not be apparent to you.
You might not, probably generally don't fully understand why a device works as well as it does.
Well, I have an example of a simple invention.
And I was curious.
I haven't used this example before.
I'm going to show you how many of you use this invention.
Do you know what a gimlet is?
How many of you own a gimlet?
Nobody.
Nobody owns a gimlet.
Can someone tell me what a gimlet is?
It's amazing.
I shouldn't be.
A gimlet is a simple tool
that everyone used to have 100 years ago.
And what does it look like?
It's made out of wire.
This is a handle.
Okay?
Do you have a gimlet now?
Now that I've drawn a picture of it?
So, what you did with those, they were really cheap.
You could buy one in 1820.
Go to a hardware store in downtown New Haven.
They'd have a whole set of them.
And you use it to make holes.
It works really well.
I find you can buy them on the Internet.
I bought one out of curiosity.
And now I use it.
The point is that inventions come and go.
The nice thing about a gimlet is, it's really nice.
It comes to a pinpoint.
And if you want to make a hole in wood,
you just push it in, and it goes exactly where you want it.
And then you just turn it a little bit, and it goes right in.
Well, we have electric drills now, right?
We're kind of used to the problem.
Once you start using a gimlet, you love it.
Because you can control it so well.
That drill, when you start drilling, it kind of bounces around,
and it doesn't make the hole where you want it.
So, there's something good about this invention.
You can go out and buy one now for very little money on the Internet.
It'll be mailed to you.
Now that I have it, I'm thinking about it all the time, for using it.
But somehow, it comes and goes.
Inventions are part of our culture that appear and disappear through time.
So, thank you.
Thank you.
I wanted to talk about another invention.
This is by way of inspiration.
But I'm getting to finance in a minute.
But I have to do these simple –
maybe someone will reintroduce the gimlet.
I don't know.
It seems like it's probably gone forever.
It illustrates the fact that modern electronic technology
has given us something maybe better.
But if you were used to using this, you'd want it.
I just don't want to use that electric drill,
because I know how to use this, and I can control it.
I'll give you another example of an important invention,
which I saw come in my lifetime.
And that's wheeled suitcases.
Okay.
I bet you have one of these, right?
A suitcase with wheels on it.
When I was a boy, there were absolutely none.
Nowhere.
No one had a wheeled suitcase.
Isn't that strange?
You'd be carrying these suitcases around,
when you put it on wheels.
So, I looked up the inventors of this.
It's not that long ago.
I thought I – oh, yeah, okay.
It was – the wheeled suitcase was invented by Bernard Seydal.
In 1972.
And his was the first one.
He had a suitcase with little wheels, four little wheels.
And you had a strap, and you'd pull it,
and it would trail behind you.
But then the other, the really important invention
was by Robert Clath.
This isn't finance, but I kind of think of it as finance.
In –
it was 1991.
And he called it the roller board.
This is what you own, right?
You own a roller board.
Right?
It has a rigid handle that collapses into the suitcase,
and it has two wheels that are horizontal.
The problem with Bernard Seydal's invention
is that it tended to flop over.
You're pulling it with a strap behind you.
And then you look back, and it's flopped over.
You can't go around corners very well.
So, we lived with Seydals for 19 years.
And it took 19 years to invent the modern roller board.
So, I actually heard from Bernard Seydal.
I wrote about him in New Financial Order.
And I got a letter from him just about two weeks ago,
or email from him.
And he said, I heard about your book.
And he thought you'd talk about me in your book.
And he said he'd like to get me to autograph it for him.
So, I said, fine, I'll send you the book.
And I sent him an autograph with appreciation of it.
But that just shows it's not long ago.
So, I guess I could ask you to reflect,
why didn't people have wheeled suitcases?
But you weren't born yet, right?
So, I can't reflect on that.
I'm thinking back to myself.
You know, it's almost something that I would do myself.
I'd put wheels on it.
But I guess you were embarrassed to do it back then.
Because maybe it seems sissy to do it.
But was everybody worried about being a sissy?
Not everybody.
Why doesn't anybody do it?
Well, Bernard Seda, I had my student interview him.
And he listened to objections.
And people told him in 1972, no one's going to buy that.
Because if the suitcase is too heavy, you just get a red cap.
You know what a red cap is?
A red cap is someone, a poorly paid person,
who stands around at train stations,
and he's wearing a red cap,
and helps you with your luggage.
That's not a good answer, right?
There isn't always a red cap to help you.
And so, obviously, you need wheels on suitcases.
But this illustrates how technology moves.
It moves sometimes slowly.
I'll give you a couple other examples from my book
about the slowness of inventions.
One is just the invention of wheels.
Did you know that in the Americas, before Columbus,
there were no wheels?
The American Indians had no wheeled vehicles at all.
Not even suitcases, nothing.
No wagons, nothing.
And then to complicate it, they've discovered,
in the late classical period in Mexico,
they've discovered wheeled toys.
And if you go to a museum in Mexico, you can see them.
They made toys for their kids.
They're not cars.
They're little jaguars and animals.
And you could roll them along the floor.
So they made the toys.
And then they thought, why didn't they think of making a wagon?
It just never occurred to them.
And another example I give in my book that I really like
is the movie subtitle.
This is an amazing thing.
When they invented movies, I gave you a Thomas Edison sound movie,
but it didn't work.
He couldn't make a sound movie.
They didn't find out how to make sound movies until the 1920s.
So they did what they, in order to give dialogue to a movie,
they'd give what they called intertitles.
They would show the movie.
And then, do you know what I'm saying?
Then they'd stop the movie, and there'd be a title with some phrase that someone said.
And then it would go back to the movie.
But it's obviously better just to put subtitles on the bottom of the screen, right?
Let the movie proceed.
You've seen movies with subtitles, right?
It works fine.
Well, it turns out that someone tried it in 1920.
There was a movie called The Chamber Mystery.
And someone made a subtitled silent movie.
But the response was bad.
It seemed like nobody liked it.
And so it wasn't for another.
Subtitles didn't come in until after sound movies were invented.
After sound movies were invented, they wanted to make movies in one language
and show them in another country.
So they had to put subtitles in so that people in another country could see the movie.
And then that's how it came in.
There's a slowness to understand or appreciate invention.
Anyway, I want to move to invention in finance.
And that's the analogies that I've just talked about are important.
So let me start with an important invention in finance that goes way back.
Well, I was going to start.
I think I mentioned last time the very simple idea of setting up a company and dividing
up shares in the company.
That's a really old invention.
That's thousands of years old.
All right, you and your friends are going to do a business.
How do we divide up the profits?
Well, let's give shares to each of us.
And the guy who's contributing more gets more shares, right?
And someone who's contributing less gets less shares.
But then we all have an incentive to make the company go.
And that's the idea of a corporation.
A corporation comes from the Latin word corpus, which is a body.
It becomes like a slave owned mutually by all the people in the company.
And your share in the company is determined by the number of shares that you own.
But I wanted to focus here.
That's an old idea.
It's an invention.
But I wanted to really focus on a particular nuance that developed.
It's called corporation.
It's limited liability.
A limited liability corporation is a corporation that guarantees that you as a shareholder
will not be liable for the debts of the company.
In England, they sometimes will put limited.
So, you can put the name of the company and after it will say limited.
But in the U.S., we just say incorporated.
So, that tells you that it's limited liability.
What it's talking about, limited liability means that somebody sues the company and the company can't pay.
They can't go after the stockholders.
So, limited liability has kind of a complicated history.
According to a history by David Moss, who is a Yale history graduate student when he wrote this,
but is now at the Harvard Business School, it started, limited liability really took hold in 1811
with a corporate law in the state of New York, which represented a significant invention.
The corporate law of New York in 1811 actually had two important components.
The first component was anybody can start a corporation.
Just file the papers with the government of New York and you've got a corporation.
There may have been some regulatory requirements.
But the point was, you didn't need an act of Congress or an act of Parliament to start a corporation.
It used to be limited liability.
It used to be very hard to start a company.
Because people would say, well, what's your purpose?
And, you know, we don't just do this automatically.
That was the first part of the New York law in 1811.
But the second part is particularly interesting.
They said, under no circumstances can the shareholders be sued.
You put in your money to the company, that's it.
You are protected by the law.
No worries about that.
Now, this was the first corporate law in the world, according to Moss, that imposed limited liability as a clear right of the shareholder.
There were limited liability clauses before, but it was never so crystal clear.
At the same time, around 1811, other states in the United States were looking at New York and saying, you're crazy.
What are you doing?
You can't sue the shareholders?
They could do something irresponsible.
And so, the state of Massachusetts at around the same year made a completely opposite law.
And they said, they made it clear that the shareholders are responsible.
You invest in a company, you're responsible.
And that's the only way it's fair, they thought.
Well, guess what happened?
New York became the financial center of America.
Nobody wanted to set up a company in Massachusetts anymore.
Because they couldn't raise money.
The capitalists were at risk.
If you bought one share in a company in Massachusetts, and the company did something criminal, let's say, or bad, I don't know, something bad,
then they might sue the company and then come looking for anybody who is among the shareholders.
You own one share in the company, so we can take everything from you.
We can take your house, your car.
Well, you didn't have a car.
You take whatever you have.
So, the rule was, be really careful before you invest in any company.
And you've got to watch them all the time.
But you know what that did?
That kept Massachusetts down.
Because nobody wanted to do that.
I mean, you'd only invest with trusted friends.
You'd never invest in just some random company.
But what happened in New York was that companies started appearing rapidly.
Because of this.
And as many critics said, a lot of companies,
a lot of these companies are fly-by-night.
They're going to go under.
We're going to find out that they weren't doing a good business.
They were just show-offs, and they go bankrupt.
But some of those companies did extremely well.
And they created a powerful New York economy.
And so, then people learned, well, yeah, you could invest in 100 companies, and 99 of them will go under.
They're all wild.
Not all of them, though.
There's one that will be the Walmart.
And it's going to make you rich.
So, the example set by New York was eventually copied by Massachusetts, by every state in the United States,
by every country in Europe, and now every country in the world.
See, it was an experiment that might not have gone well.
You know what David Moss thought?
And this has to do with framing, again.
Why is it that New York became such a capital of finance?
Because of this law.
And because it made investing fun.
And this is a matter of framing.
Moss emphasized that when you buy a share in a company, and it's limited liability,
you know that you've already put out all the money that you'll ever put out.
But you could get an infinite amount.
Well, there's no limit to the amount of money on the upside.
And he thought, that's not the way to do it.
And he said, it's just framed better as a psychologically appealing gamble.
It's like a lottery ticket.
People like lottery tickets, right?
They just enjoy the thought.
I don't know, I don't do this, but apparently a lot of people do this.
You go and you spend a dollar for a lottery, or two dollars for a lottery ticket,
and then you think, tonight I could be a millionaire.
Alright?
And so, that's just so much fun that you want to do it again.
But if the lottery ticket said,
well, you have a small probability of being a millionaire,
but you also have a small probability of going bankrupt.
We're going to come after you and take everything.
You wouldn't like that.
It wouldn't be so much fun, right?
You like to savor the possibility of getting rich.
And so, people flock to these stocks.
It's like a sport.
It's an invention of something fun to do for a lot of people.
But it has this productive side to it,
that it funnels capital to where it's needed.
So, that was an important invention.
I want to give you another example that is a variation on this.
I'm going to move forward in time.
My next invention is the,
oh, God, I'm breaking chalk here.
This goes now to China.
This is the Township and Village Enterprise, or PVE.
And I'll try to say it in Chinese,
.
Did I say that right?
Close, anyway.
So, what was this?
When China emerged from a strictly communist state,
in the early period, maybe starting in the late 70s,
but more in the 1980s,
the Chinese economy increasingly became built on a certain kind of organization
called a township or TVE.
And the TVE was like a company, a corporation,
except that it always involved the town.
So, in other words, if you wanted to start a business,
making something, making toys for export to the world,
you wouldn't just start a toy company.
You would go to the mayor of your town,
and you'd talk to the mayor and say,
I want to start a toy company as this town's enterprise.
And I want to share the profits with you, with the whole town.
Now, this is kind of unique.
I don't know if it's unique, but we don't see this in the United States.
But it proliferated.
It was actually the invention that led the initial successes of the Chinese economy.
By 1985, I believe, I have the statistics here,
there were 12 million TVEs in China.
By the mid-1990s,
most of the industrial production of China was done by TVEs.
So, then you have to ask, why?
This is an invention, but we don't see it in other countries.
Why in China?
Well, people who look back on it think that it was inventing around certain constraints
at the time in China.
And the invention got around a legal constraint,
that China, having been a communist country,
did not have all these financial lawyers.
And they did not have courts that enforced legal contracts,
the way we do in the U.S.
And that entrepreneurs in China were inhibited from starting an enterprise,
because they thought it would just be usurped by the village.
You live in a village, you start a toy company,
as soon as you start making money,
they'll just put a tax on you, or they'll take it.
That was your worry.
So, you had to involve them.
It was a fact of life, very important fact of life.
You had to involve the whole community.
You could not start a business.
You could not start a business without involving the community.
But it was a very successful invention,
because it actually led,
it actually led the Chinese economy
on its first huge successes.
Okay, I'm going to move to another example now
of an innovation in finance.
And I want to talk about inflation indexation.
.
And I could pick many.
These are examples that I like personally.
There's an infinite number of examples.
It doesn't matter exactly which example we pick.
But there's a fundamental financial problem,
and that is that the value of money changes through time.
We have inflation measured by a consumer price index.
And when inflation proceeds, the prices go up,
and so the buying power of money goes down.
And it's uncertain.
There's inflation risk that we face because of the uncertainty about prices.
This is an inflation risk that's under concern right now
after the quantitative easing that the Fed,
we'll come back to that.
The Federal Reserve is expanding the money supply dramatically
in an effort to deal with this crisis.
And some people are worried about inflation risk.
But it's a long-standing worry.
It goes way back in time.
Most debts are done in nominal terms.
.
And that means they're written in the currency units.
And if the currency becomes worthless, you're wiped out.
Why do people write contracts in currency units?
Well, it's because it's familiar with them, and so it's framing.
We're used to thinking in terms of money,
and so we write contracts in terms of money all the time.
.
So, the idea is, maybe we should start something else.
Let's not write contracts in terms of money.
Let's write in terms of something else.
And that's an invention.
But it's another invention.
It seems obvious.
Let's index our debts to some measure of inflation.
So, the invention I want to talk about first goes back to 1780.
I believe that the first indexed bond was issued in the state of Massachusetts in 1780
by the Massachusetts government.
And that was an indexed bond.
They defined a consumer price index.
They didn't call it that.
They called it the British pound.
And they said that the bond would pay you so many pounds.
They weren't using dollars yet.
They were using pounds, British pounds.
The amount of pounds you would get would be increased if inflation were to start.
So, they defined an index of commodities that you might purchase.
And that index was used to input a formula
that created inflation correction to the bonds.
So, these bonds were issued in 1780.
And it served an important purpose because the U.S. was fighting a war with the United Kingdom at the time.
And there was tremendous inflation.
So, they were very important.
But after the war, after the Revolutionary War ended,
they stopped issuing these bonds.
And they forgot about them in the United States.
Until 1997.
It's amazing.
Why did the invention disappear?
It's like gimlets.
I think maybe gimlets will make a reappearance.
Maybe some of you will buy a gimlet.
They're very cheap, by the way.
And they're very useful.
So, maybe, it seems like there's a psychological barrier toward adopting something that's not a good thing.
But they're adopting something that's a little bit complicated.
And people have trouble understanding index bonds.
And they have trouble understanding how the formula works.
And they think, you know, I just want money.
I just want money.
But then you ask, well, why didn't people learn that?
And you know, it's the same thing, isn't it?
If you look through history, we've had bouts of inflation so many times in so many different countries.
And, you know, if you buy a nominal bond, it's risky, especially if you buy a 30-year bond.
People are doing that, even today, all over the world.
They buy these 30-year bonds, denominated in dollars or euros or some other currency.
But what's going to happen to those currencies?
So, why don't you denominate your bond in something more realistic?
Well, after 1997, the introduction in the United
States of index bonds, the reintroduction in 1997, it
seemed to be started by one person, Larry Summers, who was
Assistant Treasury Secretary.
Just believed in this, and he did it.
And so, we still have them.
It got up to over 10% of the U.S. debt.
Now, under Bush and Obama, they're kind of letting them
sag now, and they're down to 6% of the U.S. debt.
But it really should be 100% of the U.S. debt
should be indexed.
So this is a kind of example of progress that is made
gradually through time.
And maybe you'll see that in the next 40 years.
I'm trying to think of how we can make these things happen.
That's an agenda for younger people who can start
innovating and changing our
finances.
Thank you.
I think you're getting over to the financial system.
So I wanted to talk about an invention that particularly
intrigues me, that comes from the country of Chile.
And it has to do with, it's a financial invention that
overcomes framing problems.
And it illustrates some of the basic concepts.
So, let me talk about Chile.
We're jumping around the world here.
Chile had a problem with, like many Latin American
countries, especially of that time, with inflation.
So, they had a currency called the peso, which
inflated enormously.
It went up, I don't have the numbers on it, but it went up,
you know, like prices went up a thousandfold.
And people were saying, we can't trust anything.
I wouldn't take a contract paying pesos.
The peso is gradually becoming worthless.
So, Chile switched to another currency called the escudo in
1960.
They said, OK, we're starting fresh.
We're starting fresh.
We're not going to have inflation.
And this is brand new.
Now we're an escudo country, no inflation.
Then, in 1975, they switched back to the peso.
The exchange rate, peso of escudo, was, one escudo was
1,000 pesos, OK, because they had had something like a
thousandfold price increase.
And then, in 1975, the exchange rate was, one new
peso is 1,000 escudos.
They went up, a new peso was a million old pesos.
OK, this is getting embarrassing.
I mean, like, can we trust anything or anybody in Chile?
So, the invention started in 1967.
People in Chile were saying, we just want stability.
You know, this is crazy.
Our prices, if I own one peso, I have a nice thousand peso
note from 1955, and I pull it out in 1975, and it's worth
nothing.
It's not even worth the paper it's printed on.
So, we've got to get stability somehow.
So, somebody in Chile had the idea, all right, maybe we
can't protect, we don't know how to protect the currency,
but we can create a unit of account that is stable in
value, and let's write contracts in this unit of
account, rather than in pesos.
So, in 1967, in Chile, they created something called the
unidad.
Unidad de Fomento.
That's Spanish for unit of development.
But what it was, was a unit of account that is indexed to
inflation.
And they said, write your contracts in terms of, and they
call them UFs.
OK?
So, everything could be written in UFs.
Forget pesos.
Because you don't trust pesos anymore.
Let's write contracts in terms of something else.
And that stuck.
Let me see.
It started out as 100 escudos.
Let me see, what was it?
I think it was, one UF was 100 escudos in, I think it was,
something like that.
I don't know.
But it was in 1967.
But by 1977, a UF was 450 new pesos.
Now, if you want to know what a UF is worth now, you just go on the Internet, and it
gives it for everyday.
And the website is, I had it written here.
What is it?
I don't know.
I think the website is valoruf.cl, but it's from my
memory.
And so, I looked up what a UF is worth today.
And I'll use the dollar sign for peso.
21,468 pesos.
So, that means that since 1977, prices have gone up
about 50-fold in Chile.
But if you signed a contract written in UFs, you're
completely protected from that.
It's a very important invention.
And it's a very important investment.
Why is it an important invention?
It's important because without it, Chileans wouldn't
index.
We don't index much in the United States.
Almost nothing is indexed to inflation.
Why not?
I don't know.
It's like resistance to wheeled suitcases.
You almost can't figure it out.
It's so obvious.
When you rent an apartment, they should index it to
inflation.
They should tell you, our apartment rents are going to
go up every month or down, depending on the price level.
When you advertise a house for sale, it should be
indexed to inflation.
Otherwise, you're just making it crazy.
You're just making Yale tuition should be indexed to inflation.
It should go up and down with the level of, that keeps its
real value constant.
But we don't seem to do it, because we can't, something is
blocking our thinking about it.
So, we have to do something like this, I believe.
And so, that's what we're doing.
And so, that's what Chile has done.
So, this is the way things are done today in Chile.
It became an invention that took hold and never left that
country.
If you rent an apartment in Chile, good chance that your
rent will be quoted in UFs.
And if you're paying a monthly rent check, this is what you
do.
So, your rent is, I don't know how many UFs.
You go to valoruf.cl.
You find out how many pesos it is.
You write out a check for that number of pesos.
Okay?
And they do this out of habit.
The amazing thing I discovered is that in the United States,
and in just about every country of the world except Chile,
alimony payments are defined in currency.
All right?
You get a divorce.
The mother, let's say, has to support children.
And the mother, let's say, has to support children.
The father is required to pay alimony for the next, until the
children grow up or indefinitely.
All right?
That's a long-term contract.
What if there's inflation?
What does it do to the value of the alimony?
Well, of course, the real value goes down.
So, shouldn't courts just index it to inflation?
Well, they do in Chile, because they've got a habit of doing
things in terms of UFs.
So, this is a great thing.
So, this is an important financial innovation.
By the way, guess how much consumer prices have gone up in
the United States since we created the Consumer Price
Index in 1913?
It's 22-fold.
And we've had a lot of inflation in this country.
22-fold, that means $1 in, something that costs $1 in the
United States.
Something that costs $1 in 1913 will cost $22 today.
That means that if you held cash between 1913 and today,
basically, you're completely wiped out.
But the inflation rate is only 3% a year.
That's 3% a year for almost 100 years is a 22-fold increase.
So, we're living with this kind of uncertainty in the United
States today.
And we're living with the fact that we've adopted the Chilean
invention of UFs.
It's interesting that this invention spread somewhat
throughout Latin America, and it stopped at the Rio Grande.
Mexico has something called UDI, which is the Mexican
version.
That's UDI, which is the Mexican version of Unidad de
Fomento.
But the rest of the world doesn't want to copy this idea.
Why is that?
Because this idea emerged out of embarrassment.
Chile had had a massive inflation, which is
embarrassing, and nobody wants to copy anything from someone
having that bad experience.
It's also cultural that we're not used to Latin American
things, just like we're not used to using gimlets.
So, we don't have them.
Let me just give one more invention.
I'll stop.
This is another financial invention.
More recently, it's the invention of the swap.
I'd like to give this example, because it relates to a couple
of our speakers.
What is a swap?
Well, the swap is a financial contract that was invented by
none other than David Swenson.
We'll be speaking soon.
He is the chief investment officer for Yale University.
He invented this before he came to Yale, when he was working
for Salomon Brothers, which was a major Wall Street investment
bank that no longer exists.
But back then, in the early 80s, he apparently, I've got a
couple of sources.
I think he is the real inventor of it.
What is a swap?
Well, a swap is a contract between two parties, usually a
fairly long-term contract, to exchange cash flows.
So, the simplest swap would be a currency swap, where one
country, there's two parties, two different companies, let's
say.
One of them promises to exchange euros for dollars,
however, every month for the next five years.
And the other one promises to exchange dollars for the next
five years.
So, they're going to exchange euros for euros every month for
the next five years.
It's a swap.
But we decide in advance on what the conversion is, what the
swap rate is between euros and dollars.
And so, that's useful for risk management purposes, because
somebody, someone in Europe may be getting dollars revenue in
their business.
They know they're going to get this revenue over the next five
years.
It's kind of a long-term contract, a long-term business
contract.
But they know that they don't know at what rate they can
convert it back into euros.
And on the other side, we have the Americans who may be doing
business in Europe, and they get euro income, and they want
to convert it to dollars.
So, they can make a contract that swaps these cash flows.
And that was the invention.
And it didn't come until the 1980s.
It's amazing that these simple ideas weren't out there.
And why weren't they out there?
Well, it may have something to do with legal uncertainty,
regulatory uncertainty.
There's something called ISDA, which was founded since the
1980s.
That's the International Swaps and Derivatives Association.
And what it does is, it lobbies lawmakers for laws that permit
swaps to work efficiently and effectively.
And so, you need a –
an organization like ISDA that will make these contracts work
as effectively as they are.
Now, swaps are a hugely important contract.
My last example, which is a sub-example from this, is the
credit default swap, which is something that – I won't put
David Swensen's name.
A credit default swap is, again, a contract between two
parties that has to do with the risk of a credit event.
So, there's a protection buyer.
There's two parties.
One we'll call the protection buyer, and the other is a
protection seller.
And it would have to do with – basically, the buyer promises
to pay the seller at regular intervals for some period of
time, and just pay – the money just flows regularly from the
buyer to the seller until an event occurs, which is, say, a
bankruptcy of some company.
It's defined in the contract.
In which case, then, the protection seller has to pay
the protection buyer.
Now, you might ask, isn't this like an insurance contract?
Wouldn't you call this insurance?
If I'm paying regular payments to somebody else, and then if an
event occurs, I'm getting insurance against default by
some company.
And I may be doing business with the company, or I may be
investing in the company's bonds, so I may want this protection.
But it looks like insurance, right?
Well, actually, there's something else called credit
insurance, which goes back to the 19th century.
There were companies in, like, 1880 that would allow you to
buy insurance against default or some failure of a company.
So, this was an institution and an invention of the 19th
century.
But credit default swaps are, what's the difference?
Well, the difference is that there's a whole culture and
regulatory environment developed around credit insurance that
limited it.
They didn't have ISDA.
They had state insurance regulators, okay?
And they just didn't have the same conceptual framework.
It's complicated.
The credit default swap was boosted by ISDA and other
thinkers who thought of how to make this into a huge, huge
business.
Credit insurance turned out, ended up being kind of limited
in its application.
And often, the credit insurers were more like consultants.
They would say, we'll insure your credit against, we'll insure
you against the default by someone you lend money to, but
we want also to be involved in your credit.
And they were involved in helping you avoid making bad
contracts like that.
So, the credit default swap became huge.
Now, I say this, let me just conclude with this.
This brings us back to our, one of our outside speakers,
Hank Greenberg, is going to talk about his company, AIG,
which failed because of errors.
It didn't fail.
It got bailed out by the government.
It got bailed out because of errors made in credit default
swaps.
I don't think that these errors were his fault, because this
happened after he left the company.
But I just want to mention this, because it's all part of a big
picture.
We had a financial invention, the swap.
Then we had the credit default swap.
And these are important inventions.
They caused a leap forward in our ability to do risk
management, but they created attendant risks.
They were new, and they weren't understood by the government.
They weren't understood well enough.
And so, a big part of what happened in this crisis was a
failure of the credit default swap market.
But that's not, to me, an indictment of financial
innovation.
I think the credit default swap was an important innovation,
and we will see more like it, and it will help make for a
better world.